This talk is about righting writing wrongs.
حديثي هو حول تصحيح الأخطاء المكتوبة
No, the sound's not faulty -- righting writing wrongs.
و لا، ليس هذا لعبا على الألفاظ
The Middle East is huge,
الشرق الاوسط واسع و مترامي الأطراف،
and with all our problems, one thing's for sure: we love to laugh.
و مع كل المشاكل التي نواجهها ، هناك أمر مؤكد : نحن نحب أن نضحك.
I think humor is a great way to celebrate our differences.
وأعتقد أن الفكاهة هي وسيلة فائقة نحتفل باختلافاتنا بواسطتها.
We need to take our responsibilities seriously,
ينبغي أن نعامل مسؤولياتنا بجدية،
but not ourselves.
و لكن علينا أن نكون أقل جدية مع أنفسنا.
Don't get me wrong: it's not like we don't have comedy in the Middle East.
لا تفهموني خطأ: لا يعني ذلك أنه ليس لدينا كوميديا في الشرق الأوسط.
I grew up at a time when iconic actors
فقد ترعرعت في حقبة استعمل الضحك فيها ممثلون كبار
from Kuwait, Syria, Egypt
من الكويت وسوريا ومصر،
used laughter to unite the region,
كوسيلة لتوحيد المنطقة،
just as football can.
تماما كما تفعل كرة القدم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now is the time for us to laugh at ourselves,
هذا هو الوقت الذي ينبغي أن نضحك فيه فيما بيننا
before others can laugh with us.
قبل أن يضحك معنا الآخرون.
This is the story of the rise and rise of stand-up comedy in the Middle East --
ان هذه هي قصة تصاعد شعبية الكوميديا الارتجالية في الشرق الأوسط
a stand-up uprising, if you will.
- انتفاضة الكوميديا، اذا جاز التعبير.
Working in London as TV maker and writer,
كنت اعمل في لندن كمنتج و كاتب تلفزيوني،
I quickly realized
و تنبهت الى أن الجماهير
that comedy connects audiences.
تتفاعل بسرعة مع الكوميديا.
Now, the best breeding ground for good comic writing
وأفضل مدرسة لكتابة الكوميديا الجيدة
is the stand-up comedy circuit,
هي مسارح الكوميديا الارتجالية،
where they just happen to say that you kill when you do well
حيث يوصف ادائك بانه “قاتل” عندما يضحك الجمهور ،
and you bomb when you do badly.
و انك سلمت الجمهور “قنبلة” اذا كان الاداء سيئاً
An unfortunate connection for us maybe,
مع ان هذا تشبيه غير مناسب بالنسبة لنا ، ربما،
but it reminds me
و لكنه يذكرني
that we'd like to thank one man for, over the past decade,
أننا يجب ان نشكر رجلا واحداً، عمل طوال العقد الماضي،
working tirelessly
دون كلل
to support comedians all around the world,
ليدعم الكوميديين في جميع أنحاء العالم،
specifically comedians
و لا سيما الكوميديين
with a Middle Eastern background.
ذوي الاصول الشرق اوسطية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Like my good friends, Dean and Maysoon, at the bottom of the screen,
مثل أصدقائي الحميمين ، دين وميسون ، في الجزء السفلي من الشاشة ،
who, two years after 9/11,
والذين قاما بعد عامين من أحداث 11/09
started a festival to change the way
بتنظيم مهرجان كوميدي
Middle Easterners are perceived in the world.
لتغيير صورة الشرق أوسطيين في العالم.
It's still going strong, with positive press to die for.
و لا يزال يزداد شعبية. و تتسابق اليه الصحافة الإيجابية.
Also, three guys working for years in Los Angeles,
و قام ثلاثة شبان كانوا يعملون لسنوات عديدة في لوس انجليس.
an Iranian, a Palestinian and an Egyptian,
وهم إيراني ، و فلسطيني ومصري
created the aptly named Axis of Evil comedy act.
بخلق فرقة كوميدية أطلقوا عليها اسم “فرقة محور الشر الكوميدية”
And wherever they went,
و أينما ذهبوا
they killed.
كان اداؤهم “قاتل”
Now, I didn't start this fire, but I did pour petrol on it.
الآن ، أنا لم ابدأ هذه الشعلة، بل كل ما فعلته اني صببت عليها البنزين.
I moved to Dubai as the head of original content
انتقلت إلى دبي كرئيس قسم البرامج الجديدة
for a Western TV network.
لشبكة تلفزيون غربية
My job was to connect the brand with a Middle Eastern audience.
كنت مسؤولا عن انتاج محتوى يكون له وقع لدى جمهور الشرق الأوسط
Now, the American head of programming
آنذاك ، أراد رئيس البرامج الأمريكي
wanted new local Arabic comedy.
تقديم كوميديا عربية،
In a thick Arabic accent, my brain went,
ففكرت بلكنة عربية سميكة ،
"Berfect."
"Berfect"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I had friends in the U.S.
أصدقائي في الولايات المتحدة
who had started a successful new tribe.
كانوا قد بدأوا قبيلة جديدة ناجحة.
And I had every intention of taking this tribe
وكان لي كل النية في نقلهم
from being outliers in the Middle East
من لاعبين جانبيين في الشرق الأوسط
and pushing them over the tipping point
و دفعهم الى ترجيح كفة نجاحهم
towards success.
في منطقتنا.
Now, as with any new idea, it wasn't easy.
كما هو الحال مع أي فكرة جديدة ، لم يكن ذلك سهل.
I had four phases to this plan.
وضعت أربع مراحل لخطتي.
First, we'd need to buy content from the West and air it.
أولا، علينا شراء برامج الكوميديا من الغرب و نبثها.
Then I'd bring my friends, and we'd show local amateurs how it's done.
ثم أقوم باحضار أصدقائي، ليرى الهواة المحليون كيفية تقديم الكوميديا.
We would film that and air it,
ثالثا: نقوم بتصوير ذلك و بثه على الهواء،
and then I could work with the local amateurs and write new comedy.
و أخيرا: أقوم بالعمل مع الهواة المحليين و نؤلف كوميديا جديدة
I excitedly presented this to the big boss,
قدمت هذه الخطة بحماس إلى المدير الكبير،
and his reaction was, "Um, I don't get it."
وكان رد فعله ، “آه، لم أفهم!"
So I retreated back to my cave
فتراجعت
and continued to support and produce comedy
واستمريت في دعم وإنتاج الكوميديا
and let my friends use my couch
و تمكين أصدقائي استخدام بيتي
as a regional operations hub.
كمرتكز لأعمالهم الاقليمية.
Now, fast forward two years, to early 2007.
بعد سنتين ، في عام 2007
The earth rotated, as did our management,
دارت الأيام ، و دارت الدائرة على إدارتنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and as if by divine intervention,
وكما لو كان ذلك بتدخل سماوي،
things came together
تضافرت الأمور
to help this revolution take shape.
بحيث ساعدت هذه الثورة على الظهور
Here's how the dots connected.
حسبما يلي
First, the Axis guys recorded a Comedy Central special
أولا، قام شباب فرقة محورالشر بتسجيل برنامج خاص بقناة “كوميدي سنترال”
that aired in the States,
الذي أذيع بالولايات المتحدة،
and it was getting great hits on YouTube.
و كان له شعبية كبيرة في “يوتيوب”.
Our new French CEO
كان لدينا رئيس تنفيذي جديد، فرنسي،
believed in the power of positive PR ...
يؤمن بقوة الآثار الإيجابية للعلاقات العامة..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and ideas du bon marche.
والأفكار “دو بون مارشي”.
Let's just say "value for money."
دعونا نقول "القيمة".
I produced in Dubai a show for Ahmed Ahmed
أنتجت في دبي عرضا قدم فيه احمد احمد
to showcase his new Axis special to a packed room.
عمله الجديد في قاعة مليئة بالحضور.
I invited our new CEO,
دعوت رئيسنا التنفيذي،
and as soon as he realized we had a room packed full of laughing infidels,
وحالما أدرك أن لدينا قاعة غاصة بهمجيين ضاحكين,
his reaction was very simple:
كان رد فعله في غاية البساطة:
"Let's make this happen.
: “هيا فلنفعلها”
And one more thing: No, don't F it up."
، و أضاف: “لا مجال للخطأ"
So I quickly went to work
ثم، بدأت بالعمل
with a great team around me.
مع فريق رائع من حولي.
I happened to find
و بمحض الصدفة وجدت
a funny guy to present it in Arabic,
شابا موهوبا وظفته ليقدم العروض باللغة العربية ،
who is originally Korean,
علما بأنه كوري الأصل،
a perfect fit for the Axis of Evil.
الأمر الذي جعله مناسباً
This is all true.
ان هذا كله صحيح.
Now, while preparing for the tour,
أثناء التحضير للجولة،
I had to remind the guys to be culturally sensitive.
قمت بتذكير الفريق بأن يراعوا الحساسية الثقافية لمنطقتنا
I used the three Bs of stand-up don'ts
و ذلك بأن يحترموا
as I call them in the Middle East:
أو بالأحرى بأن يبتعدوا
blue content, keep it clean; beliefs, not religion;
عن الجنس و الدين
and the third B, bolitics.
و السياسة.
Stay away from bolitics in the Middle East.
و قد يقول قائل:
Oh course, you might think, what's left
ماذا يبقى ما يضحك عليه الناس
without bolitics, sex and religion, how can you make people laugh?
اذا أفرغنا الجنس و الدين و السياسة من محتوى الكوميديا؟
I'd say, watch any successful well-written,
ردّي هو أن تشاهدوا أي سلسلة كوميدية عائلية
family-friendly sitcom in the West
ناجحة تعرض في الغرب
for your answers.
للتوضيح.
Now, were the Axis successful?
و لكن، هل نجحت جولة فرقة محور الشر الكوميدية؟
In five countries, in just under a month,
في خمسة بلدان ، في أقل من شهر فقط،
we had thousands of fanatical fans come and see them live.
شاهدهم الآلاف من المشجعين “المتعصبين” على خشبات المسارح،
We had millions see them on TV and on TV news.
كما شاهدهم الملايين من الناس على شاشات التلفزيون وعلى الأخبار التلفزيونية.
In Jordan, we had His Majesty the King come and see them.
في الأردن ، جاء جلالة الملك و حضر العرض.
In fact, they were so successful
و في الحقيقة كان محور الشر ناجحين
that you could buy a pirated copy of their DVD,
لدرجة أنه كان بامكان الجمهور شراء نسخة مقرصنة من ال ”DVD”
even before it was released in the Middle East.
الخاص بهم حتى قبل أن يتم توزيعه للبيع
Anywhere you go.
في منطقة الشرق الأوسط.
So everywhere we went,
و أينما ذهبنا،
we auditioned amateurs.
اختبرنا هواة في الكوميديا الارتجالية.
We filmed that process and aired a documentary.
و صورنا ذلك و قمنا ببثه كمسلسل وثائقي.
I called it "Three Guys and Wonho."
و أطلقت على المسلسل اسم “ ثلاثة شباب و ونهو” ،
It really is his name.
فهذا اسمه.
And all this TV and Internet exposure
كل هذا البث في التلفزيون و على الانترنت
has led to a great many
دفع باعداد كبيرة من الراغبين
recruits to our cause.
للالتحاق بقضيتنا.
In Dubai this year, we've just had
ففي دبي هذا العام ، شاهدنا
the first all-women's, homegrown stand-up show.
أول فرقة كوميدية تتكون من النساء،
And notice two of them are wearing headscarves,
علما بأن اثنتين منهن محجبات،
and yes, even they can laugh.
و نعم، حتى هؤلاء يستطعن الضحك.
Dubai, to me, is like a hand
ان دبي ، بالنسبة لي ، هي كاليد
that supports anyone who wants to make things happen.
التي تدعم كل من يريد أن يجعل الأشياء تحدث.
20 years ago,
قبل 20 عاما،
no one had heard of it.
لم يسمع بها أحد.
Look at it now.
لكن انظروا إليها الآن.
With an inspirational leader, I think this year,
فبوجود الزعيم الملهم،
the opening of the tallest tower in the world
فان تدشين أعلى برج في العالم هذا العام
is like adding a finger to that hand,
كمن يضيف إصبعا
that points at all those
يشير إلى كل أولئك
who spread fallacious stories about us.
الذين ينشرون القصص الواهية عنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, in three short years, we've come a long way
الآن ، و بعد ثلاث سنوات قصيرة ، فقد قطعنا شوطا طويلا
with stand-up comedy shows happening even in Saudi Arabia.
مع الكوميديا الارتجالية التي بدأت تنتشر حتى في السعودية.
These comics are now going to the New York festival.
و هولاء الكوميديون العرب استدعوا للأداء في مهرجان نيويورك.
And the Lebanese, brilliant Lebanese,
و اللبناني اللامع،
Nemr Abou Nassar, we featured in our first tour,
نمر ابو نصار ، و الذي استعرضناه في جولتنا الأولى،
has just been performing in L.A.'s legendary comedy clubs.
قد بدأ للتو تقديم أدائه على مسارح لوس انجليس الأسطورية للكوميديا
So clearly, from the inside, we are doing our best to change our image,
يبدو لنا، من الداخل ، اننا نبذل قصارى جهدنا لتغيير صورتنا المتعاظمة،
and it's exploding.
و التي تنفجر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك).
So, as for the outsiders looking in,
أما بالنسبة لمن يروننا من الخارج،
watch the CNN report on the second Amman Comedy Festival.
فشاهدوا تقرير شبكة سي ان ان عن مهرجان الكوميديا الثاني في عمان.
The reporter did a great job, and I thank her,
فالمراسلة قامت بعمل فائق ، و لها الشكر على ذلك،
but somebody forgot to send the positive PR email
ولكن أحدهم نسي أن يرسل داخليا في الشركة رسالة الاعلام الايجابي
to the person operating the automatic news ticker that appears at the bottom.
للشخص المشرف على تزويد شريط الأخبار الذي يظهر أوتوماتيكيا أسفل الشاشة.
For example, when Dean talks,
الذي يقول أسفل دين عبيد الله
the ticker says, "U.S.: Suspect gave 'actionable intel."
"الولايات المتحدة : المشتبه أعطى معلومات مشكوك بأمرها حول العملية."
Well, if you're used to listening to comedians,
إن كنتم معتادين على سماع الكوميديين
then I'm not surprised.
فلا عجب في هذا
Sadly, this leads me to another three Bs
للأسف ، هذا يقودني إلى ثلاثية أخرى
that represents how the media in the West
تعكس كيف يصورنا الإعلام الغربي
talks about us as bombers, billionaires
على أننا إرهابيون أو أصحاب البلايين
and belly dancers.
أو راقصات
Enough.
كفى
We're not all angry fanatics
فلسنا كلنا متعصبين غاضبين
who want to kill the infidel.
متعطشين لقتل الكفار.
We have a positive story to tell
بل لدينا قصة إيجابية لنرويها
and image to sell.
وصورة لنروجها.
In fact, one thing's for sure, in my experience,
في الحقيقة، و من تجربتي، فأنا متأكد من أمر واحد،
we love to laugh like hell.
و هو أننا نحب أن ننفجر ضحكا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here are three questions that I like to use
أطرح هنا ثلاثة أسئلة
to test the truthiness of our representation
أختبر بها تمثيلنا في أي
in any media story.
خبر اعلامي
One: Is the Middle East
أولا : هل يتم تقديم الشرق الأوسط
being shown in a current time
كما هو حقيقة في الوقت الحالي
and correct context?
و في السياق الصحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Two: Do the Middle Eastern characters
الثاني : هل تقوم الشخصيات الشرق أوسطية
laugh or smile
بالضحك أو الابتسام
without showing the whites of their eyes?
دون ان يظهر بياض عيونهم؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Three: Is the Middle Eastern character
ثالثا: في أفلامكم، هل يقوم ممثل شرق أوسطى
being played by one?
بأداء دور البطل الشرق أوسطي ؟
Clearly, there are wrongs that need to be righted.
لا شك أن هناك أخطاء يجب تصحيحها.
We've started in our region.
و قد بدأنا بذلك في منطقتنا.
My challenge to the rest of the world
ان التحدي الذي أقدمه لباقي العالم هو:
is please, start using
من فضلكم، ابدأوا باستخدام
positive Middle Eastern images in your stories.
صور شرق أوسطية ايجابية في قصصكم.
For inspiration, go to one of our festivals,
الذهاب إلى مهرجاناتنا سيلهمكم،
go online, drop us a line.
شاهدوا أفضلنا على الانترنت. تكلموا معنا.
Let's change the narrative together
و دعونا معا نغير مقولاتكم عنا،
and let's start righting writing wrongs.
و نبدأ بتصحيح الأخطاء المكتوبة.
I'd like to end, before going back to the Middle East,
قبل أن أعود إلى الشرق الأوسط، فاني أود أن أنهي
with a quote from one of the greatest Sheikhs
باقتباس من أحد أعظم الشيوخ
to put quill to parchment.
في تاريخ الكتابة
As my father likes to call him, "Asheikh Azubare;"
ألا و هو ”الشيخ الزبير“ كما يحب والدي ان يسميه،
as my mother would say, "Shakespeare."
و كما تقول أمي “شكسبير”
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And now we go in content
"و الآن نمضي بقناعة..
to liberty and not to banishment."
ليس نحو الإقصاء بل نحو الحرية"
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)